this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
sea radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
this is your host Roshan today I'm
interviewing sugu sugumarani co-founder
and CEO at Planet scale before founding
Planet scale sugu worked at YouTube as a
software engineer where he co-created
whites a database clustering system for
horizontal scaling of my sequel sugu
welcome to the show is there anything
you'd like to add to your background the
only thing I would add is I've been
working on databases for much longer
since the 90s where I was at informix so
that's great so you have been working
and building data systems for quite a
while I'd love to discuss how Data
Systems have evolved over the past 30
years and what are some of the
challenges we face in the modern era of
large Data Systems
before we go there let's talk about the
origination of Vitas what was the
architecture at YouTube when it was
starting to experience hyper growth both
in terms of users and Views and what
challenges were you facing this was the
year 2006 late 2006 but about three
years so three years after Google bought
YouTube
and we had actually already sharded the
database at that point I believe we had
about four shards but the number of
outages we were experiencing was growing
it was somewhat exponential we had
reached a point where there were outages
many outages every day and our backs
were against the wall
any iterative improvements you were
making were not catching up to those
outages at that time Solomon my
co-creator of Vitesse and me we kind of
took a step back together saying that we
need something else that allows us to
LEAP ahead of all these problems so he
actually went to a coffee shop spent few
days there
and created enormous spreadsheet of
every problem that we ever faced what
were the current Solutions what would be
the best solution that's an interesting
way to organize your challenges so that
you can see patterns or get a holistic
view of the potential system you're
about to design so for listeners who are
curious about a method for system Design
This may work and once you've looked at
that spreadsheet the answer was almost
obvious what needed to be done the
answer was unless there is a layer
between the application and the database
we are not going to be able to address
all these problems and all the problems
that we are predicting will come in the
future and then we started small so we
started what is our biggest pain Point
our biggest pain point at that time
where the number of connections that
were going into MySQL and the biggest
problem we had was when a primary
database went down like at that time we
had I think about 5000 connections going
into the primary database
we would perform a failover and
instantly because you know YouTube is
getting pounded by traffic
these web servers will instantly try to
make 5000 connections to the new primary
and would bring it down
so that is when we said we need a layer
in the middle that pulls connections so
that was the first version of with this
that we created
and the rest is history after that the
beauty is once you figure out that there
is a middle layer that can getting
requests and sending them to the
database people then start looking for
features in it can you do this can you
filter that out can you blacklist
queries you know so those kinds of
things that is how we test was started
and that is how it evolved interesting
of course this is a distributed database
system and it is incredibly complex to
build such systems so what were some of
the architectural decisions that you had
to make at that early stage of Designing
did you anticipate all the traffic all
the number of databases that the system
had to handle and of course there are
cap theorems and other complexities that
you have to consider so how much of the
decision making was done during the
initial stage or did you have to sort of
go back and revisit any of the
architectural decisions that you made
the most difficult decision that we had
to make was whether to write a parser at
that time it was a very difficult
decision in other words the thing is do
we use this just purely for connection
pooling or do we intend to do more with
this tool if we intend to do more to
this tool we need to understand the
queries that are coming in in order to
do that we are going to write a parser
so we said we want to eventually be able
to understand the queries that are
coming in and mediate them to the
database now decide what to do with it
what to do about that query so we the
big decision that we made was to say we
are going to write a parser I used my
old knowledge of yak at that time I had
used the act in
89 I think 89 when we were trying to
write a c plus compiler so all that
knowledge came back to me so we decided
to write a parser and that is a decision
that has definitely paid off that one
decision allowed with us to become what
it became today essentially a
full-fledged distributed database system
that is one decision
the capitalism is a very interesting
thing I think we should go over it later
but it is a very very important factor
in many of the decisions that we made
later down the line with with this
especially related to ensuring
durability and availability
those played a very important part yeah
let's definitely go deeper later virus
has a number of features that enhances
MySQL in the areas of performance safety
monitoring topology management and
sharding right and let's walk through
each of them on with us website it gives
a number of features especially in the
performance right how does videos handle
connection pooling and manage
transactions so connection pooling is
one of the first features that we did
and it is still one of the best
performance parameters for MySQL MySQL
actually has improved when we launched
with test we were on a very old version
of MySQL 5.1 which is like
supposed to be a dinosaur or Nobody
Wanna uses my so MySQL has improved but
still not enough you still benefit from
connection pooling but more importantly
connection pooling solves problems
Beyond just MySQL performance
the one thing that it does is it handles
spikes extremely well
so if you have 5000 connection 10 000
connections actually at a later date I
think it would have been a lot more I
don't even know it'll be it would have
been in the tens of thousands of
connections right going into mysqls
unless VTS was not there in the middle
when there are that many connections a
small Spike would create a domino effect
where everything starts to back up and
nothing ever completes right and because
of the fact that you type connection
pool what you would do is it would keep
the database performing at its most
Optimal Performance because we don't
make more connections to mySQL
than what it can handle at Max load
which means that if there is a huge
overload all other queries are waiting
and MySQL does not get pushed over its
limit there is a problem where once
MySQL gets pushed toward its limit it
doesn't it takes a while to fall back to
normal performance parameters so it
prevents that huge problem where an
outage causes an outage not just so
scaling up and scaling down was always
an issue yeah like if there is a sudden
huge Spike the database remains
protected and we do the best we can to
satisfy as many queries as possible got
you you mentioned earlier that writing
the query parser was the most important
decision that you ever made it should
obviously help you in query optimization
and you also mentioned something about
query deduping would you expand on how
query optimization is done yeah query
youtubing was a super cool feature
there's a story this was inspired by
this story that happened at YouTube was
when Engineers write software they make
assumptions about the data and one of
the assumptions that we had made is how
many videos can a person upload 500 you
know 500 is like you have to upload a
video every day for one year to be able
to upload 500 videos
so when we queried the table for a
user's videos
we didn't put element class
right so we say select you know select
all videos that this user has and then
display it
and it was fine until there was a person
that had 250 000 videos wow okay that's
nothing today by the way
it must be some automated borders yeah
probably it was still fine until someone
listed their profile on YouTube's
homepage
so what happens is every page hit every
home page hit ended up
pulling these 250 000 videos
what does query deduping does is if
multiple queries come
identical queries come and one of them
is already gone in and is executing
all the other queries just wait for that
query to finish
and the result is shared across all of
them
so in this particular case the 250 000
video case yes that query would hit the
database but only once
and it would hit the database again only
after it is completed gotcha so that
means you also had to implement some
sort of a caching mechanism in this
query layer this was implemented without
caching because all that happened was
the other queries just waited for this
query to return the result and they just
shared the result believe it or not we
don't know how many such due to pings it
caused but that issue never came back
ever we never faced that issue ever
again at YouTube once that feature was
implemented gotcha what other
performance benefits that you were able
to gain out of the query parser like any
other query optimization techniques that
you used the other one that was super
important
was to basically the other defense
mechanism that we did against this 250
000 video limit is to say that any query
that you send
that has no limit class
we will add a limit Clause to it but in
order to be relationally correct right
like if we write your query we cannot
just say you asked for 100 000 rows I
give you only ten thousand what we did
was we limited it to ten thousand one so
if the number of results
reached ten thousand one then we just
returned an error saying that your query
is too big so in other words you are not
allowed to query more than 10 000 rows
if you are serving the website if you
are coming for doing some analytics and
stuff you are allowed to pull as much as
you want but if you are serving the
website you are not allowed to fetch
more than x number of rows gotcha yeah
so that is another Improvement we made
from the fact that we were able so the
the advantage of farsing means that that
limit can be added no matter the
complexity of the query it could be a
join it could be anything but we
understood the query to be able to add
the limit correctly catch it another
important concept of distribution Beauty
databases are sharding what are vertical
and horizontal sharding so vertical and
horizontal sharding is essentially a
growth process that almost every company
has to go through it is it is almost
unavoidable and the first type of
sharding the company usually does is
vertical charting the definition of a
vertical sharding is if there are
multiple tables that are you start with
one database actually YouTube was just
one database the first starting we did
was to separate out
tables that are not related with each
other into separate databases so the
first charting that we did at YouTube
was to pull out
user
related information into its own
database users and videos were actually
moved into a separate database and there
were other secondary data like fraud
detection this we had hundreds of tables
there there were so many tables which
were in the other database so that was
for example that's what I would Define
as vertical sharding
then you you are allowed to scale scale
more but the limitation of vertical
sharding is that it is basically a way
to buy additional Runway it is not an
indefinite scaling solution because
eventually that's what happened is our
user database grew beyond what yeah
exactly and also like at the most you
can think of four or five
vertical contractors
so once we hit that limit we realize
that now we have to go horizontal
horizontal sharding means that one group
of users are on one shot another group
of users are on a Not A Shard that
becomes more difficult in the case of a
relational database mainly because
relational database is inherently
complex because it defines relationships
between multiple entities the simplest
way I would put it is the biggest
challenge that every company goes
through that we also had to go through
was to convert that relational database
into a hierarchical database would you
explain what that means in other words
the relational term is getting rid of
the many-to-many relationships
that you only have one-to-many
relationships one to one or one to many
relationships
it's not that many to many relationships
don't exist but we weaken those
relationships we can as in in terms of
like taking out the constraints exactly
there is no strong constraints and those
relationships are maintained
asynchronously by the application for
example so we had to rewrite the
application
to not rely on these many-to-many
relationships and once that is done
then there is the mechanism of sharding
which is mostly a database only
operation culture the first part is
actually rewriting the application to
not rely on the many-to-many
relationships gotcha but even with
sharding like now the application layer
has to have some sort of knowledge about
where different sets exactly so that was
actually the evolution of Vitesse I
would describe it is that when we did
sharding at YouTube the application had
all knowledge of the sharding topology
is what what we called it
and where with us is today is that
knowledge is now taken back from the
application and lives inside with Tess
and the application is unaware of that
knowledge does not need to know that
information so that was long Evolution
that took the tests from where we were
then to where we are today okay so that
means of the application don't have to
worry about the internal distribution of
data it still gets the view of a single
database exactly and all the on reduced
complexity because of that yeah so in
this particular case if there are many
too many relationships those queries
will work today they did not work then
because there was uh the Vitesse parser
and analyzer were not sophisticated but
now we have added those sophistications
they will still not work optimally
because the fact that you have to go to
different charts to fetch different
types of data right and you have to have
a working cache to be able to join the
data together has all those overheads
exist but it at least will work for you
how does indexing work in a single
database system I know when I create an
index queries that use those indexes
perform better because MySQL in the
internally uses those indexes but if
data is distributed across multiple
databases does white as abstract away
creating and using the underlying
indexes if you create an index on say
The Logical view of the data
that's a very exciting question because
there's a beautiful story behind this I
don't know if you know about Michael
Stonebreaker yes yeah so when I was at
informix there was this company called
illustra that Michael Stonebreaker was
the founder of so his theory at that
time was that the index of a database
need not be an internal implementation
of the database
so he founded illustra and talked about
these plugable indexes I think the their
best product at that time was they built
their own plugable indexes the spatial
index for example was a plugable index
of illustra I think it is now a
first-class citizen of postgres the
plugable index capability but that was
his invention at that time informix
acquired illustra so I actually moved
myself into illustrike just because I
was so excited about it
of course that kind of went nowhere
later for various other reasons but that
idea and excitement has always remained
in with me and when we implemented with
tests we built plugable indexes from the
ground up inside with us as as first
class citizen type of a thing so the
test allows you to Define your sharding
scheme and your secondary indexes as
code gotcha would you would you go a
little deeper in into explaining both of
those yes so one of the big arguments
that people are they don't have it as
much now but these used to be huge
arguments where they will say should you
Shard by range or should you chart by
hash right if you're short by range you
have this problem you have hot row
problems you know those arguments were
endless
that's when it became obvious that there
is no single Silver Bullet in terms of
shady so it depends on the application
use case exactly the application use
case but not only that the application
use case may dictate one type of trading
today and it may change tomorrow exactly
so we needed answers to all these
scenarios so that's when we came up with
sharding function so the shardings came
in with this is actually what we call as
a Windex or a v index is basically a
function that takes a value as input and
produces an output and that output is
range based sharded so if you wanted
hash sharding you just wrote wrote a
hash function the beauty of this is that
there was one with test adapter that was
sharded by vendors you know vertical
like you shared your they were a
multi-tenant system and they were
sharding by vendors and they had a Json
file and when they adopted with test all
they did was wrote code that read this
Json file and gave you the output
everything else just worked like magic
so that's the first part of sharding but
that same concept what we did was we
extended it for cross chart indexes so
in the case of a cross shot index you
take an input but it's not just a
function instead you go and query your
lookup table
saying that where can I find this row
and then it becomes a cross shot index
like for example it will be easier to
understand with an example let me see a
think of an example let us say I buy
from you
so in other words order let's call it
the I place an order with you right the
order row has two keys
it has me and it has you when I make a
decision I have to decide whether the
order role lives with me or with you
okay so if the order role lives with you
let's say you are the merchant and I
query show me all the orders that sugu
has bought I would have to go to all
shards because I might have brought from
everybody
so this lookup index is what we call it
what it would do is when it inserts the
row in your table it will also insert an
entry into the lookup table saying that
sugu has ordered from
from you so when you then query the
database saying that show me all the
artists you guys want the lookup table
will say if you query these three shards
you will find all the orders that sugu
has bought
you one of the not disadvantages like
the challenges with charting is
it may become very one-sided right like
as in like the way data is created
unless you have some randomized keys
involved a single database may get
additional rows and some databases may
may not have new keys at all
so how do you like so you have to
constantly sort of fight this
rebalancing the databases even in fact
like if you add additional databases you
have to continuously resize exactly how
does the writers take care of free
sharding the simple answer is that's
what basically what we did at YouTube is
as database grows organic growth right
so if databases grow organically
all you do is keep restarting which
means that keep splitting your shards
into two like we started at four shards
right when I left YouTube we had like
256 charts
gotcha and the beauty of this splitting
is because every time you're splitting
into two eventually you can outgrow any
growth because it's purely exponential
like initially you are sharding almost
every three months six months Etc right
once we had hit 256 our thought was we
may never Richard ever again
oh wow okay it's like the you know the
chessboard story that you hear yeah
exactly at some point of time you
basically exceed any possible
astronomical numbers yeah exactly yeah
yeah so that is one scenario the other
scenario which happens a lot more with
the multi-tenant situations
a single tenant grows immensely huge
this goes back to the scenario where I
said where you cannot predict how your
application is going to evolve yeah so
this is a case where the application or
the data I evolved in a way where just
like even putting that one tenant
in their own database may not be
sufficient imagine I am a small store
and suddenly I get Walmart as my you
know as my customer exactly they are
like 100 times everything else I have
right so if you get something of that
size at that time what you have to do is
you have to change your sharding scheme
so this is where the Windex comes into
play you know you can now re-index your
table and say now I want to use a
different sharding scheme that
distributes the data better for me
gotcha and does this happen live in the
sense like or do we have to bring
databases down and it is all live so the
core technology in with us which is
which is one of the best things we ever
built in with this is what we call as
the materialization we call it V
replication
but it's essentially a materialization
feature where you can say that please
materialize this table in a different
form somewhere else in a shortage setup
so if you don't like your current Windex
you can say rematerialize this table
using a different index and then cut
over the traffic to the other table when
the materialization is complete and all
these things can be performed like
either through GUI or so command line
one line yeah yeah basically these are
what I would call Basic Primitives
within with f and you compose them
actually we replication has met an
innumerable number of use cases it has
helped with data migration it has helped
with schema deployment
it has helped with resharding it has
helped with re-indexing it's one of the
best Technologies we ever built it is
super exciting it is also used by for
our boost feature in Planet scale where
if a query is underperforming you say
please build a cache for this query so
that it performs better gotcha and we
sort of briefly touched upon topology
Management on the website there's
something called re-parenting is it
related to consistence algorithms or are
they different is it the right time to
bring cap theorems and stuff like that
yeah yeah yeah so what am I what I say
may feel like I'm overreaching but I'm
pretty confident of what I'm going to
say vitess actually uses what I believe
is a more generalized form of consensus
which actually allows you to come up
with more practically useful topologies
like the way I would put it is today the
cloud is very complicated the cloud
architectures are very complex there are
zones there are regions you know there
are failure boundaries and people have
different tolerances depending on their
business and stuff so there is no one
size fits all when it comes to giving
durability guarantees so similar to the
Windex approach what we have built in
with this is basically a plugable
durability policy which means that I can
come and say I want my durability to be
like the English words for this would be
I want cross-sell durability right I
want cross Zone durability or I want
cross region durability or it may be
more specific I have only two regions
and I want cross region durability but
then if one region goes down I want to
be able to operate in in a diminished
fashion so all these flexibilities are
provided by with us and they give you
the same guarantees that a consensus
algorithm like raft or paxos would give
you
and I actually tried to describe the
theory crafting behind this in a Word
document in a Google doc and somebody
said oh this is too big you cannot post
it as a Blog so okay I'll split it up so
it is now eventually ended up as an
eight series eight part blog series that
explains the consensus behind the
generalized theory behind consensus
algorithms that with this uses to
guarantee the durability constraints
that users want would you be able to go
through that blog post like in a short
period like in five minutes
let me try so the basic thing is that
it's basically a top-down approach like
the problem with raft or pack source is
that they were solutions that were built
and adopted by people that had specific
problems but if you flip it around
saying that what is your problem that
you're trying to solve and then let's
build a solution that solves it the way
I would Define the problem is what we
want is distributed durability which
means that if a node fails basically if
I acknowledged that I have accepted your
transaction and that node fails that
data is somewhere else that I can pick
up and continue from so that is
guarantee number one guarantee number
two is availability right if a few nodes
in the system fail my system should not
say I'm going to stop it should continue
to make progress as long as it can
continue to provide the durability
guarantees that you have requested so
you know if you have two zones
and I want cross Zone durability and
there are five nodes in the other zone
three nodes go down it is fine because I
can still save my data in one of the
available nodes and continue processing
and the third one is automation which
means that if a node fails you shouldn't
have to wake up someone in the night
the system has to be able to heal itself
without data so I think those are the
three things that you look for in a
consensus system
and if you built a system with those
objectives you may not end up with
something like pacsource and actually I
would say there are essentially two
types of consensus system there is the
lock free consensus system which is
paxos and the systems that whatever what
I call lock based which actually raft is
actually a lock based more of a
lock-based consensus system and the
fundamental difference between them is
the time component if you look at paxos
there is no time in the description of
the algorithm it could take a
millisecond or it would take 20 years it
doesn't matter in a log base system
because a log base system tend to prefer
the first attemptor to win like if I say
I am going to perform a failover then I
have preference to win that operation
which means that anybody else that comes
after me has to wait for me to finish so
you need to put a time frame because if
I attempt and then fail right after
sometimes somebody else should pick up
the fact that I failed right so that's
the reason why a Time component is
needed so your log base systems add time
components and then perform their
operations whereas a system like Praxis
does not have a Time component and most
practical systems actually need this
time component the reason is because
real life is based on the fact that I
cannot wait two years you know for you
to perform so after a while you have to
put an end to it and move forward so
most consensus systems actually use
Timeless component but it's slightly
deeper topic let me know if I've gone
too far deep this is good because like a
listener is definitely they encounter
the challenges challenges of consensus
systems again and they have to pick
between paxils versus raft and like
you've kind of explained why we need
practicality and like most systems kind
of pick raft because of that
practicality yeah totally and the other
reason why raft is better is because it
also includes failure detection which
paxos doesn't and you cannot build a
consensus system without failure
detection
so that is the thing the one Improvement
that we made over raft is that is
actually a paper called Flex pack source
which actually makes a modification in
how you select your quorums which gives
you a huge flexibility in terms of your
deployments like for example
at YouTube we had like 75 replicas
for each primary and if you imagine
running a consensus algorithms with 75
nodes right but we did and how did we do
it is because of this modified Quorum
definition which basically the way we
run it at YouTube is if one other node
other than the current primary has my
data that is sufficient for my
durability and in the 10 years that we
operated at you know millions of QPS we
have never been in a situation where
both the node that accepted the right
and the node that saved the data failed
at the same time and you mentioned all
these configurations are customizable as
in you can turn on knobs for the right
reliability and safety trade-off that
you can make yeah exactly and that was
actually the reason why I ended up doing
this study right where which ended up in
this 8 series blog post which is why is
it that we are not using pack Source why
are we able to give you the same
guarantees that a consensus system gives
you not just YouTube Right slack runs at
millions of QPS jde apparently runs like
30 million QPS on there because sale day
they all use with s and they are a huge
test user and none of them have come and
told me ever that they lost Trader
because you know so that's why I said
like what is the difference between all
these algorithms and that's how I ended
up with this I'll put a link to your
serial blog post series it's an
interesting read for the listeners yeah
it's a little deep unfortunately it's
the nature of the Beast it is a very
it's a very difficult topic yeah the
distributed systems are hard like yeah
yeah and you also have on with us site
has something called re-parenting is it
so something finding the new master or
is it correct yeah yes that is part of
this consensus so initially we had this
as code within with us now we have built
something called VTR which stands for VT
orchestrator which performs all these
operations so re-parenting detecting
what has failed and re-parenting is a
process of choosing a new primary so
this is all part of that consensus
protocol that we now actually officially
codified into this tool and finally like
we can also talk about safety because we
have written your own query parser I
think you can do query rewriting
blacklisting and query killer or do you
want to explain those benefits yeah
before going into that the biggest fear
the biggest anxiety I always had at
least in the early days was
what if I mess up a query rewrite right
I get a query and I rewrite it wrong
and the interesting thing was at some
point of time I even got paralyzed about
making changes right how do you like I'm
afraid to break the system that is now
you know serving all of YouTube you want
a feature I don't know I'm not too sure
so I over time we started getting scared
of making changes to the system and at
that time our technically it was talking
to our Tech lead Ally he's still at the
Google by the way
and he said something extremely wise to
me which is we got to trust our tests
so if you don't feel confident about
your changes write more tests now that's
a very important wisdom for all software
Engineers yes so I took that to heart
went down and just blasted the thing
with all kind of tests like any possible
failure that I could think of you know I
wrote it and also made sure that the
tests had enough code coverage so I
followed that discipline like that has
never left me from that day on and that
is a curse that every with this engineer
carries today
that now we can be sure of the quality
and reliability of virus because of that
culture yeah yeah so it does like I
wrote five lines of code you can't push
it
where are the tests where are the tests
that demo that you need to write tests
that demonstrate the feature you are
doing
those are separate tests and you need to
show that all failure modes are covered
you need to also show that all
meaningful code paths have been covered
so it's a pretty tall plane but but the
thing is companies rely on on the
accuracy of the system so there's no
choice right yeah and like in terms of
like how does one configure blacklisting
and like how do you decide when to
collect query or how to send it like is
it something that the user needs to
configure or there is some automation
within that there is some defaults about
the query killing for example has
defaults and you can tune it up or down
and there are people most people believe
it or not most oltp systems want the
same defaults there are only a few
Corner cases here and there that want to
play like for example HC said we don't
want this limit they completely extend
it to like not two hours what was like a
query killing that was like 30 seconds
right uh it's he said we want to make it
two hours
but barring those Corner cases most
people are very happy with just the
defaults that we test provides which is
within 30 seconds if if a query takes
longer than 30 seconds it's probably not
worth it for oltp exactly yeah so and
yeah we talked about all the oltp use
cases are there companies or firms that
are using vitess or Planet scale for
even analytics use cases because you get
the benefit of distributed databases and
probably some what's the right word some
big data processing capabilities right
right so we have traditionally always
encourage people to export the data out
to an analytics system
but there is actually a few trending
changes that I'm noticing that may bring
back some analytics into the test the
first one is the materialization feature
of with this people are starting to play
with that and what that allows them to
do is like keep cheap aggregate tables
materialized that they can query
instantly and it's very cheap to do it
within with us because it's just one
system right
realization and then it's ready for you
it gives you the benefits of a like
single store and you don't have to do
all the etls exactly so that is Trend
number one Trend number two is more I
read a blog post I need to find the
person that are saying that this big
data people are starting to get
dissolution because it is becoming more
clutter is is what I'm hearing most
people that have big data have it big
mainly because they don't know what to
get rid of yeah exactly yeah in the
sense like the complexity increases and
it's always an operational challenge
correct correct correct so I don't know
where that is going though I mean there
is Snowflake and that seems to be doing
well but as long as there are companies
like snowflake that are giving
meaningful value you right to customers
there is no reason for with us to try to
get into that area is what I think
gotcha in terms of like exporting data
obviously like because with s has
additional metadata and additional
intelligence when you export data do you
export from MySQL or do you export from
fit as like does Vitas has additional
integration tools to export data I mean
this has been the reason why it cannot
be my uses MySQL because it's a sharded
system right and when you want to export
data from a sharded system you want a
unified view of that charted system and
with test gives you a grpc API
essentially
and it also gives you something very
elegant which is that when you want to
do ETL if you look at these etls do ETL
tools they do some very awkward data
dump and then catch up and then resync
and it you always worry is it correct
like did it miss any rows right you
always wonder so what with this is we
call it V stream give you is an accurate
materialization of the what it does is
it gives you an API saying that an API
where it's a you need to insert this you
need to update this you need to delete
this so that's kind of what the API
gives you and you subscribe saying that
I want to materialize this table it
doesn't differentiate between data that
already exists from rows that are
changing in the table you will get
events and if you apply those events
when the thing catches up the entire
table would be materialized on your
target without you knowing there is no
separate copy phase there's no dump
phase as well this one API fulfills the
entire need okay that's great and that
is the reason why we're able to build so
many Tools around it because of the
Simplicity of this API gotcha and
viruses of course is an open source
software and it has earn it has
graduated to the maturity level on cncf
and Planet scale is a managed service
built on top of wides what additional
features does Planet scale give for
users and Enterprises yeah the way I
would put it is if the test is the
engine Planet scale is the car
like people that have to use with us it
has a large number of levers essentially
you need to employ a team to be able to
run with this whereas with Planet scale
it is readily available but Planet scale
gives you certain value adds that we
test does not have and in my opinion
they are really really huge they are
really awesome the biggest one for
example is the schema the schema flow is
so simple that I as a developer if I
want to use a database I don't need to
go wrestle with you know a DBA or sorry
about that like it's basically become
self-service for you so that is one of
the biggest things that planet scale
adds and the other one is for example
the Boost is a new thing which is built
on with this is V stream based on the
noria PHD thesis which basically allows
you to
materialize partially materialize
queries in memory as a cache and make
them more efficient gotcha so there are
basically value adds that planets
basically Planet scale really packages
with this you know extremely
user-friendly and Powerful manner gotcha
and you talked something about schema
changes would you go a little deeper
yeah yeah so the in a traditional system
right you want to do a schema change
what do you do you write the schema
right and then you give it to the DBA
and then they review it and they want to
say you have to make changes but after
all this happens when the schema deploys
things may still break it is it's the
nightmare of everybody you know the
engineers nightmare TV this nightmare
to keep the database from not failing
and uh the other problem with the schema
change is it doesn't really flow well
with my development cycle right like I I
check out code make changes and I make
corresponding SEMA changes so that is a
completely different workflow from my
checkout exactly like schema changes has
been one of the biggest headaches for
software development for everyone right
so now what we have done is we have
integrated schema change as part of your
developer flow so when you check out
code
we check out a database for you to work
with and when you add schemas you are
adding schemas to your local database
and just like you merge your code back
into your main branch you also have a
workflow to merge the schema back into
your main database and does it also
provide forward and backward
compatibility that is actually the
greatest thing that we test can do that
I don't know anybody else can do it's
because of this materialization feature
you deploy the schema and things have
broken and now you want to undo it yep
and widgets can undo your schema change
with no data loss yeah to the extent
possible right there are some things
that are theoretically not possible but
what is theoretically possible it will
do like for example you've added a
column and let's say your website is
broken you've added a column and you've
inserted you know 10 rows and now you
want a revert what about those 10 rows
right yeah exactly so what we test will
do is it will reverse replicate those
rows into your Source table
obviously without the column
but you can at least revert back to your
old Source table and continue and then
fix forward later as needed and the
technology there is deep because we need
to have an understanding this is where
the now the decision of building the
parser comes back right because we can
understand queries we can understand
schemas we can understand the diffs
between the source and Target table and
make all this work exactly yeah are
there other features that are available
on planet scale yeah the other big one
is which is again based on
materialization is a one-click migration
right like let's say if you are on a
different database like you know RDS or
something and you want to migrate to
Planet scale what we can do is you click
a button and this weird application will
materialize all your tables into the
planet scale database and then you can
switch your traffic and while you are
switching traffic we will actually
replay these events into your Source
gotcha okay so if something goes wrong
you can go back and continue so this
makes migration typically these types of
migration take you know six months one
year some companies actually just walk
away they just give up because migration
data migration is one of the hardest
things so in our case in my opinion we
have trivialized that thing with just a
click of a button gotcha and like videos
of course works on MySQL family of
databases are there any plans for it to
sort of work on other relational
databases not today every once in a
while it is so tempting
every three or four days you know the
thought comes up but it is very
important to stay focused and make the
current solution work in my opinion this
is a high level opinion but many people
would agree with me
an application should not over exploit a
database
an application should use a database for
its bread and butter features right
don't go into elaborate foreign because
those are eventually going to hurt you
if you have to scale stick to simple
queries stick to point queries stick to
index scans right those are the bread
and butter of a database don't do stored
procedures and you know there's so many
crazy things you can do with the
database but the more you do that the
less flexible you become in your yeah
yeah migration is going to be a
challenge is going to be a challenge so
if you did something like that then it
doesn't really matter if you're using
postgres or MySQL right because you're
just using the database for it for such
things I would say all these databases
do that job well okay gotcha and in
terms of like what are the plan future
features for Planet scale any important
changes that are coming
I can't talk about we are building lots
of cool features and we will announce
them as they come but Vitas features
that's an open source project I can
definitely talk about those things and
we are making some pretty core changes
in with tests especially the one big
change that we are making is make with
us more approachable previously it was
full of manholes you could go and tweak
anything you like and make anything you
want
but now that we have seen all these use
cases we know that some of these use
cases are very you know peripheral and
so we are making some opinionated
changes and we're shooting those down so
that we can move forward even faster
gotcha and is there anything that we
missed talking about either of fittest
or Planet scale that you want to talk
the only thing is I haven't had enough
time to talk about how excited I am
about planet scale the amount of
interest that we are getting I have not
seen excitement like this about a
database in the last 15 years I can tell
you the last time I have seen this much
excitement was probably when I was at
employment
like that time databases databases
databases and I see that now today which
is so exciting and if listeners wants to
contribute to vitals or know more about
planet scale or about you how can they
reach out to you I'm reachable on
Twitter and with this slack is one of
the best communities we have ever built
very positive very welcoming very
accommodative slack Channel you can go
there and ask anything and for Planet
scale planetscale.com there is plenty of
ways to contact Planet skilled people
and thank you for these really wonderful
questions I completely enjoyed talking
to you
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening